A Guide to the Rives-Troubetzkoy Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #2313
Rives-Troubetzkoy Papers
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
2313
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Container List
- Correspondence, Receipts, Statements, etc., of the Rives Family, chiefly of William Cabell Rives, Sr. and his wife Judith Page Walker Rives, and their children Ella Rives, Amelie Rives, Francis Rives, William Cabell Rives, Jr., and Alfred Landon Rives, covering the years 1800-1855. (Box Box I)
- Correspondence, Receipts, Statements, etc., of the Rives Family, including some material shedding light on William Cabell Rives, Sr.'s opinion of secession and the Civil War, covering the years 1856-1874. (Box Box II)
- Correspondence, Receipts, Statements, etc., of the Rives Family, including will and settlement of the estate of William Cabell Rives, Sr.(1868), covering the years 1868-1874. (Box Box III)
- Correspondence, Receipts, Statements, etc., of the Rives Family, including the will and settlement of the estate of Judith Page Walker Rives(~ 1882), autobiography of Judith Page Walker Rives, papers re: Grace Church(1882- n.d.), covering the years 1875-1889. (Box Box IV)
- Business and Personal Correspondence of the Rives Family, chiefly the correspondence of Alfred Landon Rives as General Superintendent of the Panama Railroad Company, mainly with E. L. Oppenheim, and correspondence between Alfred Landon Rives and T. R. Allen regarding investments in Washington state. His interests Railroad Stocks and Mining Stocks. Material pertaining to the economy of Peru. Last Will and Testament of Ella Rives. Last Will and Testament of Sadie C. Rives(wife of Alfred Landon Rives). Covering years 1887-1890. (Box Box V)
- Business and Personal Correspondence of the Rives Family, chiefly Alfred Landon Rives and his connections with Panama Railroad Company, the Panama Canal, the Veracruz to Pacific Railroad, the Maryland Trust Company, and T. R. Allen in Washington state, covering the years 1891-1898. (Box Box VI)
- Correspondence, invitations, calling cards, and other undated material, chiefly of the Rives women, particularly during their various stays in Paris. (Box Box VII)
- The original manuscript of the Life and Times of Madison, by William Cabell Rives, Sr., a 3-Volume work published by Little, Brown and Company in 1859 and 1868, ca. 1000 pages. (Box Box VIII, parts A and B)
- Miscellaneous literary manuscripts, chiefly of Judith Page Walker Rives(Mrs. William Cabell Rives Sr.), including poems, short stories, essays, and translations from French. (Box Box IX)
- An empty scrapbook. William Cabell Rives Ledger 1820-1827. 4 Alfred Landon Rives notebooks. (Box Box X)
- Architecture and Engineering Texts and Notes of Alfred Landon Rives, mainly in French. (Box Box XI)
- Architectural notes, textbooks, and drawings of Alfred Landon Rives, mainly in French. (Box Box XII)
- Architecture and Engineering Blueprints of Alfred Landon Rives. (Box Box XIII)
- Plans and Achievements of the Interoceanic Canal at Panama, mainly in French, and Alfred Landon Rives's ideas on them. (Box Box XV)
- Oversize Architectural Drawings of Alfred Landon Rives
  Note: This is a preliminary listing of Rives' drawings in Oversize Tray 40 (folders I -III) and Oversize Tray 41 (folders IV -VIII). For the most part, these are tracings of drawings he made while in Europe in the 1850's as the best examples of bridges employing the latest in construction design and technology, These drawings were repaired by the Barrow Laboratory in Richmond in November 1975 and July 1982. Drawings of buildings in Oversize Tray 8 are not listed
  - Folder I: England
    - Sandon. "Plan of the Seventy Feet Entrance to the Sandon [Essex County] Dock" plan, cross section, [elevation], I. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - [ ? ]. "Chemin de fer de Liverpool a Bijry, Viaduc sur le Canal Company's Wharf et sur Back Leeds Street, Prolongment [Extension] de Tithe Barn Street" elevation, plan, I. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. details of plans and elevations, I. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - [ ? ]. "Wild's wrought iron [canal] lock gates" interior and exterior elevations, cross sections, plans, details, I. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - Liverpool. "Eighty Feet Gates Huskisson Lock Liverpool" plan, transverse section, cross section-, sectional plan, I. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. details, I. f (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - [ ? ]. "Pont en Tole [iron plate] a Poutres Tubulaires [tubular girders] Chemin de fer anglais [English]" elevation, plan, cross section, I. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
  - Folder II: England- Newcastle & Berwick Railway
    - "High Level Bridge [between Gateshead and Newcastle]" plans, pier footings, level of carriage road, level of railroad, II. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. general elevation, II. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. elevation of pier, II. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 2" elevation, sectional plan, II. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 3" longitudinal section, details, sectional details, II. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 4" transverse section, sectional plan of piers, detail of piers at roadway, II. f (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 5" details of plans and sections of girders, cornices, parapets, wood bearers, II. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 6" cross section details: roadway and footpaths, II. h (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 7" details: footings of ribs and tie chains, II. i (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. " No. 8" general elevation and plan: approaches, II. j (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 9" cross section and longitudinal section: approaches, II. k (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
  - Folder III: England- London & North Western Railway; Great Northern Railway
    - [ London?]. "London & North Western Railway Hayden Square Branch, Lattice Bridge over Great Prescott Street and Goodman's Yard, No. 1" north elevation, plan, cross sections, plans of foundations, III. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 2" details of elevations and sections of iron work, III. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 3" details of elevations and sections of iron work, III. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 4" details of plan and elevation of roadway, III. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - Newark. "Great Northern Railway, Bridge over Newark Dyke, No. 1" elevation, plan, III. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. "No. 2" details of elevation, plans, and cross sections, III. f (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. " No. 3" details, III. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
    - d.o. details, III. h (Oversize Oversize Tray 40)
  - Folder IV: France
    - Agen. "Pont-Canal d'Agen [canal on bridge]" general elevation, general plan, details of elevation and cross section, IV. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Canal lateral a la Garonne[River]" details of elevations, IV. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. details of elevations and sections, IV. c.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. elevations and details, IV. c.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Cintres [arches] du Pont-Canal d' Agen" sectional elevation, elevation w/ construction supports, details, specifications, IV. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Bercy. "Pont sur la Seine[River]'' 3 elevations, one w/ sectional details of pilings, IV. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - "Pont Double sur la Seine[River]" longitudinal section of half of one arch, IV. f.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Pont sur la Seine[River]" elevation of viaduct, details of elevations and plan of arches, IV. f.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Pont double sur la Seine a Bercy" details: cross section of roadway and railway, IV. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. details: cross section of railway and roadway, IV. h (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Panneau superior du garde-corps internediatiaire" detail of guard rail, IV. i (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Candelabre a gaz en dehors du pont" detail of gas lamp on side of bridge, IV. j (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Candelabre a gaz du pont avec son Souhassement" detail of gas lamp with its base, IV. k (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Calais. "Pont Tournant a Double Vole sur la Cunette [channel] No. 1" elevations, plans, IV. 1 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Details des Ferrures, No. 2" longitudinal section of iron components at pivot, IV. m.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. plans and details of pivot components, IV. m.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. " Details des Ferrures" cross section, plan, details of iron components, IV. n (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Dunkirk. "Pont tournant de la citadelle a Dunkerque, [turning] Systeme de Mr. Raffeneau, No. 1" elevation and plan of half of bridge, IV. o (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "No. 2" details of turning and structural components, IV. p (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Lyon. "Viaduc sur la Soane[River]" details of elevation; plan of cornice (Signed by Rives, 1854), IV. q (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. details: longitudinal section, cross section, plan, construction supports (signed by Rives, 1854), IV. r.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. details (rough pencil skecthes), IV. r.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Montlouis. "Pont de Montlouis" elevations, plan, sections, construction supports, IV. s (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Nogent. [Bridge] "Traverse de la Valle de la Marne[River] a Nogent" elevation, plan, IV. t (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - [ ? ]. "Chemin de fer de Paris a Strasbourg, Tete d'aval du Souterrain de haut-barre" [entrance of tunnel] elevation (signed by Rives 1854 July 18), IV. u.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. pencil sketches of elevation and plan (signed by Rives 1854 July 21), IV. u.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Station de Hochfelden" elevation (signed by Rives 1854 July 19), IV. u.3 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Station de Hochfelden" plans of basement, first floor, and second floor (signed by rives 1854 July 18), IV. u.4 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Pont sur le canal de la Marne[River, au Rhin a Vendenhaim" plan (signed by Rives 1854 July 15), IV. v.l (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. horizontal section (signed by Rives 1854 July 14), IV. v.2 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Station de Vendenhaim" elevation and plans (signed by Rives), IV. v.3 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. ". de Paris al la frontiere de'Allemange ... 2 elevation, plan (signed by Rives 1854 July 13), IV. w (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Guetin. "Pont suspendu de Guetin" elevation, plan, details, IV. x (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. elevation of one span, detail: plan, section, guard rail, etc., IV. y (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - [ ? ]. "Pont Levis" [draw bridge] details of operating components, IV. z (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Rhin. "Pont Tournant sur le chenal [channel] de Vacken, Canal de la Marne[River] au Rhin, No. 1" elevation, sectional plan, longitudinal section, component details, IV. aa (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. sectional elevation, details of operating components, IV. ab (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - La Chaussee. "Chemin de fer de la Disdre[River], Viaduc No. 7 bis sur la Chaussee[River?] elevation, plan, IV. ac (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Chaumons. ''[Railroad] Viaduc de Chaumons au travers de la Valle de Suiz" elevation, plan, specifications (signed by Rives 1855 Mar 25), IV. ad (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
  - Folder V: Belgium, Germany, Switzerland
    - Belgium
      - "Chemin de fer Belge Rehnan,...Viaduc de la gueele du chemin de fer d'aise a la fronteire Belgi" elevation (half of bridge), plan of foundations, sectional elevation, details of elevation and construction supports, V.a (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Germany
      - Dirschau. "Chemin de fer de Berlin a Konigsberg, Pont a trellis sur la Weichsel[River] a Dirschau, No. 1" elevation, plan, V. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. " No. 2" sectional elevation, V. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. " No. 3" detail of elevation, V. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - Bietigheim. "Viaduc sur la Valle d' Enz[River] pres de Bietigheimen Wurrtemburg" elevation, sectional plan, V. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. sectional elevation, details of elevation, V. f (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - Switzerland
      - St. Gall. "Brucken und Thalubergange der St. Gallischen Eisenbahn, Blatt XV, II. Brucke uber die Sitter[River] bei St. Gallen" elevation, plan, details, specifications, V. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - Rumlang. "Brucken und Thalubergange der Schwiezerischen Centralbahn Linie Basel-Olten, Blatt II, III Thalubergange bei Rumlingen" elevation, plan, details, specifications, V. g (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - Olten. d.o. "Blatt III" "IV Brucke uber die Aare [River] bei Olten elevation, plan, details, specifications, V. i (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt IV" "Details zu Blatt III [above]" details of iron work, elevation, cross sections, V. j (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt 5" "Details zu Blatt III [above]" details of iron work, elevation and sectional plans, V. k (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt IX" "X Brche ber die Aare[River] bei Bern" elevation, details, and specifications, V. 1 (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt X" "Details zu Blatt IX [above]", V. m (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. Blatt XI" "Details zu Blatt IX [above]" cross section, V. n (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. " Blatt XII" " Details zu Blatt IX [above]" horiszontal section, V. o (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt XVI" "Details zu Blatt XV" cross section, V. p (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
      - d.o. "Blatt XVII" "Details zu Blatt XV", V. q (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
  - Folder VI: Russia
    - Sebastopol. "Docks de Sebastopol" plan, longitudinal section, cross sections, VI. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - St. Petersburg. "Pont sur la Neva[River] a St. Petersburg, No. 1" elevation, plan, cross section, details, VI. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "No. 3" "Details des macconeries [stonework]" elevation, plans, VI. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. elevation, plans, VI. d (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. " Details des piles" elevations, plans, details, VI. e (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - d.o. "Pont tournant" sectional-elevation, sectional plan, VI. f (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
  - Folder VII: United States
    - District of Columbia. "Foundation of Pier No. 2, Potomac [River] Aqueduct" plan and specifications, VII. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - District of Columbia. " Potomac [River] Bridge, Pier 5, 10, 11, 12 with the arches dependent on them, showing the progress of Construction, March 1833" details of elevation, VII. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - District of Columbia. "Map showing proposed canal from Cabin John Bridge to the Ches & Ohio Canal for transporting materials plan, cross sections, VII. c (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
  - Folder VIII- Unidentified
    - [ ? ] stone arch bridge, elevation and plan, VIII. a (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)
    - [ ? ]. iron arch bridge crossing " Alexander's Island" elevation of part of bridge, plan of foundation, VIII. b (Oversize Oversize Tray 41)